<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<title>David jensen -  Unfinished</title>
	<subtitle>Unfinished projects</subtitle>
	<link href="http://burningbroccoli.se/feed/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href="http://burningbroccoli.se/"/>
	<updated>2019-10-05T02:00:00+02:00</updated>
	<id>http://burningbroccoli.se/</id>
	<author>
		<name>David Jensen</name>
		<email>david.lgj@gmail.com</email>
	</author>
	
	<entry>
		<title>The knit counter</title>
		<link href="http://burningbroccoli.se/projects/knitcounter/"/>
		<updated>2018-06-24T02:00:00+02:00</updated>
		<id>http://burningbroccoli.se/projects/knitcounter/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://burningbroccoli.se/img/knitcounter/sm-small_battery_square.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Knitcounter with small battery&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you ever find yourself knitting a sweater you may notice that most knitting patterns has instructions like &lt;code&gt;repeat between * and * for 34 rows&lt;/code&gt; or some such. And if you are like me your thoughts might wander,
and, what row was I on now again?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of knit counters, and of course a lot apps. I wanted
mine to be small and light. The dream was to be able to use it as
the marker for start of round. This ways I couldn&#39;t possible miss
pressing the button, counting up a new round.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CURRENT STATUS: broken&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;build&quot;&gt;Build &lt;a class=&quot;direct-link&quot; href=&quot;#build&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://burningbroccoli.se/img/knitcounter/sm-circuit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Circuit with attiny85&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can obviously build this a lot smaller, but I wanted to use stuff
I already had at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A way to large proto board that I sawed to smaller size.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Large 12mm button&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small 6mm button&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A AVR ATTiny85 micro controller&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A capacitor over the power to smooth it out. I&#39;ve read that
it&#39;s a good thing to have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;0.96 Inches OLED i2c display.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Lithium-Polymer battery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-micro-controller&quot;&gt;The micro controller &lt;a class=&quot;direct-link&quot; href=&quot;#the-micro-controller&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ATTiny85 is a nice little bugger. If you are fine running it at 1MHz
or 8MHz you don&#39;t need any external crystal, maybe just a capacitor. You
can fake USB with the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.obdev.at/products/vusb/index.html&quot;&gt;V-USB&lt;/a&gt; project, play sounds
with the high frequency PWM (at leas higher than a normal arduino). It
also happens to have a very nice low power mode. You can send it to sleep
and it will consume very little until an interrupt, triggered on one of
it&#39;s pins, wakes it up. This is the main reason I choose this particular
micro controller, more on that later in the &amp;quot;code&amp;quot; section!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also several Arduino &amp;quot;cores&amp;quot; you can use, so it&#39;s easy to program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to build a small circuit so I could program it with my Atmel AVRRISP II.
&lt;img src=&quot;http://burningbroccoli.se/img/knitcounter/sm-isp.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ISP Circuit&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you don&#39;t need to use a programmer! I just happen to have one,
but in this case an &lt;a href=&quot;https://create.arduino.cc/projecthub/arjun/programming-attiny85-with-arduino-uno-afb829&quot;&gt;Arduino will do just fine.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-display&quot;&gt;The display &lt;a class=&quot;direct-link&quot; href=&quot;#the-display&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://burningbroccoli.se/img/knitcounter/sm-screen_and_circuit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Oled display&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a smallish OLED display lying around, a gift from a friend. It is
rather small, but for displaying just some numbers its quite the overkill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s an i2c no-name display, but it has SSD1306 circuit on it like most other! I tried to get Adafruits &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adafruit/Adafruit_SSD1306&quot;&gt;SSD1306&lt;/a&gt; library working with it, but failed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some googling I found another nice library: &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/tinusaur/ssd1306xled&quot;&gt;tinusaur/ssd1306xled&lt;/a&gt;. With this I got
some progress!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For simplicity I used the font that came with the library, that gave
quite small numbers, but hey it was a very simple to code 😃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-code&quot;&gt;The code &lt;a class=&quot;direct-link&quot; href=&quot;#the-code&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/davidlgj/kniterator&quot;&gt;https://github.com/davidlgj/kniterator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted the counter to a have a long battery life, preferably months.
It wouldn&#39;t do if it lost power during a project. Since most of the time
it just sits there, it&#39;s a perfect match for the deep sleep mode the
ATTiny85 has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code is simple, a one push of any of the buttons wakes it up. The
display lights up and presents the current count. Pressing the large button
increases the number, the smaller button decreases. After a couple of
seconds it turns off the display and powers itself down again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is lots of room for improvement, larger numbers for instance. You
could also have several counters, use the small button to cycle between
them. Large button to increase, long click to decrease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also had plans to save the number to the small EEPROM inside the
ATTiny85, so it never would loose count!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-is-it-finished%3F&quot;&gt;But is it finished? &lt;a class=&quot;direct-link&quot; href=&quot;#but-is-it-finished%3F&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well. No. It&#39;s broken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When i started I only had a bit of a largeish battery. It added to the
weight stuck out at the bottom.
&lt;img src=&quot;http://burningbroccoli.se/img/knitcounter/sm-with_large_battery.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;with large battery&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One nice thing with it thouhg was that it fitted nicely below the display.
For ease of use I didn&#39;t solder the display directly onto the proto board.
&lt;img src=&quot;http://burningbroccoli.se/img/knitcounter/sm-battery_between.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;with large battery&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later I got a new much much smaller battery. Yay! Soooo much lighter.
&lt;img src=&quot;http://burningbroccoli.se/img/knitcounter/sm-small_battery.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Knitcounter with small battery&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But know the display stuck out from the proto borard in an ugly way,
I couldn&#39;t have that could I? So off I went and soldered it directly
onto the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I must have done something wrong. It broke the display,
its just black. Kaputt. Dead. Some testing leads me to believe the ATTiny85 is alive and kicking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought a new, smaller display from Adafruit, but it doesn&#39;t have the
same pin count so it&#39;s not a drop in replacement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here, as always, I got stuck. I have managed to procure a new display
that looks to be of the same type as the old. One day I might try to
remove the broken one. One day...&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>The foot counter</title>
		<link href="http://burningbroccoli.se/projects/footcounter/"/>
		<updated>2019-04-24T02:00:00+02:00</updated>
		<id>http://burningbroccoli.se/projects/footcounter/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;video controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;http://burningbroccoli.se/img/footcounter/example.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Sorry, your browser doesn&#39;t support embedded videos.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I broke my first &lt;a href=&quot;http://burningbroccoli.se/projects/knittingcounter/&quot;&gt;knitting counter&lt;/a&gt; I had
an idea: We all have a screen with us all the time, the phone. I know,
not a new or a novel idea, and not the first time I thought of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Tangent: I still think our phones are ridiculously underused for stuff.
And I don&#39;t understand why I can&#39;t just plug it into my laptop and use
the keyboard and screen?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you knit you usually use both hands. So why not use your feet!
So I built a simple two key keyboard (with A and B buttons) and a web app
to keep the count.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;hardware&quot;&gt;Hardware &lt;a class=&quot;direct-link&quot; href=&quot;#hardware&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://burningbroccoli.se/img/footcounter/sm-assembled.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;knitting counter made for the foot&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Hardware is super simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adafruit.com/product/3500&quot;&gt;Adafruit Trinket m0&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adafruit.com/product/1501&quot;&gt;Adafruit Trinket&lt;/a&gt;. Both works,
but the m0 starts up more quickly and is easier to program.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A proto bord&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;two push buttons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some wiring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some sort of box&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use internal pull-ups in the trinket so you don&#39;t even need a resistor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;code&quot;&gt;Code &lt;a class=&quot;direct-link&quot; href=&quot;#code&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve lost the source code, but it was just a copy paste of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.adafruit.com/adafruit-trinket-m0-circuitpython-arduino/circuitpython-hid-keyboard-and-mouse&quot;&gt;Adafruits keyboard example&lt;/a&gt;. The
only thing I changed was that i changed it to send &amp;quot;B&amp;quot; instead of
&amp;quot;Hello World\n&amp;quot; (row 18).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that I now have a two key keyboard, yay!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second part of this is the a simple web app with two counters.
You can try it at &lt;a href=&quot;http://burningbroccoli.se/foot-counter/&quot;&gt;http://burningbroccoli.se/foot-counter/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code for it is on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/davidlgj/foot-counter&quot;&gt;davidlgj/foot-counter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-is-it-finished%3F&quot;&gt;But is it finished? &lt;a class=&quot;direct-link&quot; href=&quot;#but-is-it-finished%3F&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ll, that depends on your definition of finished. It doesn&#39;t really work.
So if that is a problem, then no, it&#39;s not finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&#39;s wrong with it you might ask. Doesn&#39;t it up the counter when you press
the buttons? It does, but you now what else a smart phone does? It goes to
sleep when you&#39;re not using it! Which means you have to wake it up before
you can use your foot to press the buttons... kinda defeats the purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The embarrassing thing is that I didn&#39;t figure this out until I had a beta
tester actually use it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>The clock</title>
		<link href="http://burningbroccoli.se/projects/theclock/"/>
		<updated>2019-07-24T02:00:00+02:00</updated>
		<id>http://burningbroccoli.se/projects/theclock/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;video controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;http://burningbroccoli.se/img/clock/test.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Sorry, your browser doesn&#39;t support embedded videos.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a work in progress. I got the idea from a &amp;quot;smart&amp;quot; clock I saw. It was quite nice.
Looked like a brick with large colorful pixels. Can&#39;t find it anymore though. Anyway
it could show the weather, mail etc. I liked it, but it was expensive (&amp;gt;€100) and closed
to their app for control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bit later i saw &lt;a href=&quot;https://hackaday.com/2019/06/12/ikea-cloud-lamp-displays-the-weather-with-esp8266/&quot;&gt;this nice IKEA hack&lt;/a&gt;.
Its a IKEA cloud lamp that changes color depending on the weather and even flashes for
lightning storms! Very nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-plan&quot;&gt;The plan &lt;a class=&quot;direct-link&quot; href=&quot;#the-plan&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan is to build a smart clock for my sons room, it would be super cool if it could
be the hub for some kind of voice control, but first off I want it to tell what the
weather will be for the upcoming day. I asked my son, and he&#39;d rather have an analog
clock instead of a digital, so I bought a cheap ordinary wall clock. It had no numbering,
I guess to look clean, so that is something I will need to fix in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to line the clock with RGB leds so I could mark out the weather approximately
where the hour mark is. This means the clock can tell the weather for the upcoming 12
hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m planning to use a Raspberry Pi Zero W for the brains of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-build-so-far&quot;&gt;The build so far &lt;a class=&quot;direct-link&quot; href=&quot;#the-build-so-far&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://burningbroccoli.se/img/clock/sm-workspace.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;clock in my workspace&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any sane person would here go and buy a nice Adafruit led
strip and just line the edge of the clock with it. But I
like to use what I already have in my stash, and one of the
things I have are several
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adafruit.com/product/1260&quot;&gt;Flora Neopixels&lt;/a&gt;
(I bought two 20 packs that where on a ridiculous sale).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to use 8 of them, to make it a bit easier to solder
and to not overwhelm the Raspberry Pi Zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The neopixel needs 3 wires, power and a signal, and that
sinal needs to be chained to the next pixel. That means
three wires between each of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking around my workspace for some wire I happened to see
some copper tape that I bought to experiment with. The tape
is supposed to be used in the garden to create a barrier
for slugs. It has a copper foil over a paper/plastic back.
So you can&#39;t tape a circuit together, but you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; solder
to it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://burningbroccoli.se/img/clock/sm-threelanes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;copper tape as wires&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The middle lane of tape is the signal, and since it needs
to chain the neopixels together I took a flat screwdriver
and just scraped away a spot where the neopixel should be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://burningbroccoli.se/img/clock/sm-soldered.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;copper tape as wires&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Works like a charm! I also soldered three wires to it. The plan
is to drill a hole through the backplate and place the raspberry
pi zero on the back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now it&#39;s time for the software... and that&#39;s where it&#39;s
hanging in limbo right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://burningbroccoli.se/img/clock/sm-soldered.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;copper tape as wires&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Future plans involve speakers or buzzer for alarm, camera for
keeping track of intruders (or waving to turn of alarm!)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>The mouse trap</title>
		<link href="http://burningbroccoli.se/projects/mousetrap/"/>
		<updated>2019-10-05T02:00:00+02:00</updated>
		<id>http://burningbroccoli.se/projects/mousetrap/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://burningbroccoli.se/img/mousetrap/sm-rigged.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;rigged trap&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a a problem. It was small furry and super cute. And it pooped
everywhere. The mouse had already foiled a couple of traditional traps
we set for it so I knew I had to take matters into my own hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is actually not an unfinished project. Its not nice looking,
well built or good code. &lt;strong&gt;But it caught the mouse!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;hardware&quot;&gt;Hardware &lt;a class=&quot;direct-link&quot; href=&quot;#hardware&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PVC pipe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two metal plates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arduino&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small servo (small enough to be driven directly by the arduino)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small metal pin, the kind use to fasten knitting needles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Duct tape&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Popsicle sticks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copper tape (I used the one used for keeping slugs out of your garden)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some wooden planks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some screws&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;build&quot;&gt;Build &lt;a class=&quot;direct-link&quot; href=&quot;#build&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The build is quite simple. A trigger at the end of a PVC pipe triggers a
closing mechanism on the other side. The trick is that the pipe is so long
the mouse doesn&#39;t have a chance to bolt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://burningbroccoli.se/img/mousetrap/sm-pressure_plate.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;trigger with peanut butter&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;quot;pressure plate&amp;quot; is to popsicle sticks with copper tape on them.
A bit of a broken popsicle stick in the middle keeps them from touching
until the weight of the mouse is on it. Btw peanut butter is great for
mouse traps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arduino code just polls with a &lt;code&gt;digitalRead&lt;/code&gt; and sweeps the servo
at the first hint of any critters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-guillotine&quot;&gt;The guillotine &lt;a class=&quot;direct-link&quot; href=&quot;#the-guillotine&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;video controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;http://burningbroccoli.se/img/mousetrap/test.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Sorry, your browser doesn&#39;t support embedded videos.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The closing mechanism is super simple, the metal plate is a bit heavy and
when the servo removes the pin it falls down. Sawing a bit down into the
wood makes sure the mouse can&#39;t push get a hold and push it up.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
